Guide to the Herman and Conway Associates Records TAM.094
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Herman and Conway Associates Records
1923-1966, (Bulk 1948-1966)
1948-1966
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Herman and Conway Associates
TAM.094
3 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
Herman and Conway Associates was a labor relations consulting firm founded in the 1940's as a successor to Robert Maisel Associates. In its work on behalf of employees and employer associations, the firm dealt with the major labor and management relations issues that pervaded the post-World War II era. The collection includes some of the the firm's correspondence, memorandums and clippings. NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Herman and Conway Associates, a firm of labor relations consultants, was the successor to Robert Maisel Associates. Although the exact year of succession could not be ascertained, the change was made sometime during the late 1940's. In its work on behalf of employees and employer associations, the firm dealt with important issues in labor- and management relations during the post-World War II era. Material on issues such as Communist involvement in labor organizations, government versus private ownership, health-care providers, public utilities and related topics are to be found within this collection. Richard Conway, while figuring in some of the correspondence and memos, does not appear to have played a central role. As far as one can judge from the records extant, Harry C. Herman had primary responsibility for the administration of the firm. He served in the infantry during World War II and reached the rank of lieutenant colonel. He was decorated with the Purple Heart twice and received the Silver Star and the Croix des Services Militaires of France. Mr. Herman was also instrumental in founding the Naval War College in Washington. He died on February 23, 1984 in Boca Raton, Florida.
Scope and Content Note
The collection is organized in one series of subject files, arranged alphabetically by title. The files contain correspondences, memoranda, Senate and House bills, reports, newsclippings, and examples of union literature. Clearly this small collection does not represent a full record of the firm's work; there are gaps in documentation, and some items appear to be missing. The collection reflects management responses to the growth in influence and membership of America's organized labor force from the 1940s to the mid-1960s. Many case-files are concerned with alleged Communist influence and infiltration in unions and labor-management conflicts.
Files on the National Farmers Union (NFU) contain documents and articles concerning possible links between this organization and the Communist Party. The report entitled "A Total Basis for Executive Judgment and Evaluation of Trade union Forces in the Food Industry" details the left-wing activity in unions associated with the food industry. One such group was the united Packinghouse Workers Union; its president, Ralph Holstein, is profiled. It was not possible to determine if this was written by a member of the Herman and Conway Associates team, but it seems that the firm was involved in management's attempt to bolster their relations with the more moderate unions of the industry. Also relevant to the issue of communism and unions are files on the United Electrical Workers (UE). These focus on the wrangling between the UE and the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers. At issue was the representation of the Radio Corporation of America workers in Lancaster, PA. Files of clippings, notes and reports on the recording industry's strike following the Second World War highlight activities of the American Federation of Musicians and its colorful president James Petrillo.
Schenley Distillers is the only subject in this collection for which extensive correspondence has survived. An exchange of letters between Mr. Herman and Mr. Phil Shays, Schenley's Director of Personnel and Labor, is included. Also included is correspondence between Mr. Herman and Louis Rosenstil, Chairman of Schenley Industries. The working relationship between the firm and Schenley Distillers lasted about five years (1945-50). During that time Herman and Conway Associates carried out their investigation into the problems which existed between the distillery and unions at various Schenley plants. Reports are based upon recorded observations and personal interviews. Charles Scofield, a member of the Herman and Conway investigatory team, figures prominently in reports and correspondence. Extensive correspondence included exchanges between Herman and Phil Shays, Schenley?s Director of Personnel, and Louis Rosenstil, Chairman of Schenley Industries.
Files on Bonneville, Hells Canyon, Missouri Valley, Niagara, St. Lawrence, and the Tennessee Valley Authority deal with the issue of government versus private ownership of electrical power. Herman and Conway Associates appeared to have been actively engaged with the subject, but it was not entirely clear who engaged them or for what specific purpose.
NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Arrangement
The files are grouped into one series.
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
A complete run of Interpreting Labor News, a newsletter produced by Herman and Conway is available at the Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The provenance of this collection is unknown. The accession number associated with this collection is 1967.002.
Industrial relations consultants.; Hydroelectric power plants |x Finance |x Law and legislation.; Hydroelectric power plants |z United States.; Electric utilities |x Government ownership.; Labor unions and communism -- United States.; Memorandums.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Schenley Distillers; United Packinghouse, Food, and Allied Workers; National Farmers' Union (U.S.); American Federation of Musicians; United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America; Conway, Richard; Herman, Harry C.; Shays, Phil; Holstein, Ralph
- Container List
  - American Federation of Musicians, 1937-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Federation of Musicians, undated, 1943-1948, 1954-1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Federation of Musicians: Clippings, undated, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Federation of Musicians: Clippings, undated, 1944-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Trade Fair Issue, undated, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Association of Actors and Artistes, undated, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bethel and Mt. Aetna Telephone, 1946-1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bethel and Mt. Aetna Telephone: Clippings, undated, 1954-1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bonneville Power Administration, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Conesta Telephone and Telegraph Co., 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Durlacher and Co., undated, 1945-1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - General Bronze, undated, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - General Foods, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hells Canyon, Idaho Project, 1952-1955 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Hells Canyon, Idaho Project, undated, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - International Brotherhood of Teamsters: Agreements, undated, 1947-1949, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Kings County Lighting Co., 1940, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Labor-Management Relations, undated, 1948-1957 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Mt. Sinai Hospital, 1958-Mar 1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Mt. Sinai Hospital, Apr 1959-1960, Feb 1963 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Mt. Sinai Hospital: Clippings, undated, 1953, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Missouri Valley Authority, undated, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - National Farmers Union, undated, 1942-1966 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - National Farmers Union: Clippings, 1945-1966 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - National Maritime Union, 1946, 1906-1961 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - National Maritime Union, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Niagara Power Project, 1946-1948, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings, 1948-1955 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Niagara Power Project, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Niagara Power Project, undated, 1951, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Niagara Power Project: Clippings, 1950-1957 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Nuclear Power and Labor, undated, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Ohio Utility Seizure Bill, undated, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Pension Plans, undated, 1941-1943, 1954-1958 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Permuit CO., undated, 1954, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - St. Lawrence Seaway, 1951-1957 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - St. Lawrence Seaway: Clippings, 1951-1955 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Schenley Distillers, 1943-1950 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Schenley Distillers, undated, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Schenley Distillers, undated, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Schick Inc., 1954 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Southern Industrial Economics, undated, 1952, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Tennessee Valley Authority, 1951-Apr 1957 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Tennessee Valley Authority, May 1957-Nov 1957 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Times Square Stores, undated, 1949-1961 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - United Electrical Workers Union, undated, 1943-1958 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - United Electrical Workers Union: Clippings, 1945-1950 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - United Electrical Workers Union: Clippings, 1949-1950, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - United Seamen's Service, 1960-1963 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Utilities, 1923, 1950-1954 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Utilities, 1955-1961 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Utilities, undated, 1947-1956 (Box 3, Folder 10)